Guide to the David Hamburg papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Correspondence
  - Subseries III.2: Institutions
    - World Health Organization, 1977-1995 (Box 394, Folder 1)
    - Yale University, 1989-2000 (Box 394, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III.3: Chronological
    The series contains miscellaneous correspondence in original chronological order.
    - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 706)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1996 (Box 707)
    - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 708)
    - Correspondence, 1997-1999 (Box 709)
    - Correspondence, Jan 2000-May 2000 (Box 710)
    - Correspondence, May 2000-Sep 2000 (Box 711)
    - Correspondence, Oct 2000-Jan 2001 (Box 712)
    - Correspondence, 2001 February-undated (Box 713)
- Series IV: Stanford University
  Correspondence, writings and speeches, meeting minutes, research data, marked-up background material, academic conference presentations, and student projects dated from 1951-1999 relating to HAMBURG's work at Stanford as a faculty member (since 1961), his work on non-human primates (NHP) there, his work on the SU Board of Trustees and the SU-Institute for International Studies Board of Visitors, and the Human Biology Middle Grades Curriculum Project. Of note is the correspondence with Jane Goodall and other NHP researchers in Gombe, and materials on late 1960s higher education controversies at Stanford and elsewhere. Series organized into five subseries, material within subseries is organized chronologically. See also the Commonwealth Fund correspondence file in Series III.2 (supported much of Hamburg’s research in early 1970s).
  - Subseries IV.1: Faculty Materials
    The series consists of correspondence, memoranda, notes, drafts, teaching materials, typescripts, students’ projects and dissertations, and research materials, documenting Hamburg’s teaching and administrative career at Stanford’s Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, serving as Reed-Hodgson Professor of Human Biology, and as chair of psychiatry at Stanford University School of Medicine. At the School of Medicine Hamburg established a new department of psychiatry and behavioral sciences, distinguished by its breadth of research on behavioral biology, especially in relation to mental illness. The series also documents his collaboration with Dr. Jonas Salk, participation in NIMH Research Task Force, and work on IOM program committee ( not to be confused with Hamburg’s later IOM tenure)
    - Subject files, 1959-1976 (Box 395)
    - Subject files, 1959-1974 (Box 396)
    - Center for Advanced Studies in the Behavioral Sciences., 1962-1975 (Box 397)
    - Faculty-Related Materials, 1963-1972 (Box 398)
    - Salk Institute Drug Conference, critique of pending legislation, 1965-1974 (Box 399)
    - Subject files, 1966-1971 (Box 400)
    - Subject files, 1966-1972 (Box 401)
    - Subject files, 1967-1976 (Box 402)
    - Subject files, 1968-1974 (Box 403)
    - Subject files (Box 404)
    - Subject files, 1969-1976 (Box 405)
    - Unesco Conference on Aggression and follow-up projects, 1970-1974 (Box 406)
    - Subject files, 1970-1979 (Box 407)
    - Subject files, 1970-1979 (Box 408)
    - Subject files, 1970-1977 (Box 409)
    - Subject files, 1971-1971 (Box 410)
    - Subject files, 1971-1972 (Box 411)
    - Subject files, 1971-1976 (Box 412)
    - Subject files, 1972-1972 (Box 413)
    - Subject files, 1972-1972 (Box 414)
    - Subject files, 1972-1973 (Box 415)
    - Subject files, 1972-1976 (Box 416)
    - NIMH Research Task Force, 1973-1973 (Box 417)
    - NIMH Research Task Force, 1973-1973 (Box 418)
    - Subject files, 1973-1973 (Box 419)
    - Subject files, 1973-1973 (Box 420)
    - Subject files, 1973-1973 (Box 421)
    - Subject files, 1973-1974 (Box 422)
    - Subject files, 1973-1975 (Box 423)
    - Subject files, 1973-1976 (Box 424)
    - Subject files, 1974-1974 (Box 425)
    - Subject files, 1974-1974 (Box 426)
    - IOM program committee amd NIMH Research Task Force, 1974-1975 (Box 427)
      not to be confused with later IOM tenure
    - Subject files, 1974-1975 (Box 428)
    - Subject files, 1974-1976 (Box 429)
    - Subject files, 1975-1975 (Box 430)
    - Subject files, 1975-1977 (Box 431)
    - Subject files, 1971-1982 (Box 815)
    - DAH departure from Stanford faculty., 1975-1980 (Box 432)
    - Faculty-Related Materials - Student dissertations, 1960-1975 (Box 443)
    - Faculty-Related Materials - Student dissertations, 1960-1975 (Box 444)
    - Faculty-Related Materials - Professional Organizations, 1953-1969 (Box 445)
    - Faculty-Related Materials - Professional Organizations, 1970-1979 (Box 446)
  - Subseries IV.2: Non-Human Primate Research
    The series consists of correspondence, memoranda, notes, conference presentations, primates. Box 440 formerly contained 10 reel-to-reel audio tapes of a Hamburg-Goodall presentation during the Burg Wartenstein Conference #62 (August 20-28, 1974), "The Behavior of Great Apes" organized by David Hamburg and Jane Goodall These audio recordings are now available in digital format. The NPR files document in detail the 1975 incident in Gombe, Tanzania, when for of his students, studying primate behavior under the direction of Jane Goodall were abducted by armed rebels, and Hamburg spent 10 weeks negotiating their release. The series also contained oversize blueprints for Stanford Primate Facility, and chimpanzee photographs, separated to Series XI.
    - Rationale, 1959-1975 (Box 433)
      Stanford Primate Facility blueprints oversized, shelved with Realia in box 811
    - Subject files, 1970-1973 (Box 434)
    - Subject files, 1970-1973 (Box 435)
    - Subject files, 1971-1976 (Box 436)
      Chimp photos removed to AV
    - Subject files, 1972-1978 (Box 437)
    - Subject files, 1973-1974 (Box 438)
    - Correspondence with Jane Goodall and her mother relating to Gombe Kidnap, 1973-1976 (Box 439)
    - Hamburg-Goodall conference presentation., 1974-1974 (Box 440)
    - Gombe Kidnap, 1974-1976 (Box 441)
    - Gombe Kidnap, 1975-1979 (Box 442)
    - Subject files, 1970-1979 (Box 818)
  - Subseries IV.3: Board of Trustees
    The series contains correspondence, general trustees’ mailings, meeting minutes, reports, and other materials relating to the activities of the Stanford Board of Trustees. David Hamburg was a member and a vice-chairman of the Board from 1988 to 1995.
    - Board Meetings and correspondence, 1979-1992 (Box 447)
    - Board Meetings; Indirect costs billing controversy materials, 1990-1994 (Box 448)
    - Board Meetings; Indirect costs billing controversy materials, 1991-1995 (Box 449)
    - Contains SPICE/IIS materials relating to Education for Conflict Resolution, 1995-2002 (Box 450)
    - Board Meetings and correspondence, 1999-2003 (Box 816)
    - Board Meetings and correspondence, 1999-2003 (Box 817)
  - Subseries IV.4: Human Biology Materials
    As the chair of psychiatry at Stanford University School of Medicine David Hamburg helped to found The Program in Human Biology. The series contains correspondence, notes, and typescripts relating to establishing the original Stanford University curriculum on human biology, and relating to a later Human Biology Middle Grades Curriculum Project, an attempt at adaptation of the SU Human Biology program to the middle school level. The Human Biology Middle Grades Curriculum Project also contains materials and writings on Puberty and Adolescence.
    - Mixture of background and writings on Puberty and Adolescence, 1971-1981 (Box 451)
    - Original SU Curriculum Human Biology, 1970-1975 (Box 452)
    - Human Biology Middle Grades Curriculum Project, 1975-1996 (Box 453)
  - Subseries IV.5: Background Materials
    Third-party typescript materials and various printed matter, frequently underlined or with Dr. Hamburg’s notes, and used as a basis of his later works. The majority of files are related to Hamburg’s activities as a member of Stanford faculty and administration, however the series also contains background materials on primate research, human biology and adolescence, and background materials received by Hamburg as a Board of Trustees member.
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1944-1975 (Box 454)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1957-1975 (Box 455)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1960-1960 (Box 456)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1960-1970 (Box 457)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1960-1974 (Box 458)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1962-1973 (Box 459)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1963-1976 (Box 460)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1965-1974 (Box 461)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1966-1974 (Box 462)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1967-1967 (Box 463)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1967-1971 (Box 464)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1967-1976 (Box 465)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1967-1976 (Box 466)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1968-1974 (Box 467)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1969-1974 (Box 468)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1970-1971 (Box 469)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1970-1976 (Box 470)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1970-1979 (Box 471)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1970-1979 (Box 472)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1971-1972 (Box 473)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1971-1976 (Box 474)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1972-1973 (Box 475)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1972-1976 (Box 476)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1973-1974 (Box 477)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1973-1976 (Box 478)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1974-1974 (Box 479)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1974-1974 (Box 480)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1974-1976 (Box 481)
    - Faculty-Related Background Materials, 1976-1978 (Box 482)
    - Primate Research, 1947-1975 (Box 483)
    - Primate Research, 1967-1973 (Box 484)
    - Primate Research, 1970-1976 (Box 485)
    - Primate Research, 1971-1975 (Box 486)
    - Primate Research, 1973-1974 (Box 487)
    - Primate Research, 1974-1977 (Box 488)
    - Background Materials for Board of Trustees, 1988-1999 (Box 489)
    - General Background Materials, 1969-1976 (Box 490)
    - General Background Materials, 1961-1979 (Box 491)
    - Background Materials on Adolescence, 1954-1979 (Box 492)
    - Miscellaneous and notes, 1970-1979 (Box 493)
    - Background Materials on Human Biology, 1966-1975 (Box 494)
- Series V: Institute of Medicine (IOM)
  Materials dating from 1967 to 1982 relating to Hamburg's work as president of the Institute of Medicine (IOM) in Washington DC. Materials in the IOM series relate to Hamburg's time as IOM President, 1975-1980, and his later correspondence as IOM member, but not to his collaboration with IOM as the Carnegie Corporation President, such as CISAC (documented in the grant files of the Carnegie Corporation of New York records and in Carnegie Corporation of New York series of this collection). The series contains general background, working papers, memoranda relating to various public health and health policy issues of the late 1970s. Also contains materials relating to the history and organization of the Institute of Medicine. Series organized into two sub-series: general/chronological and background; sub-series are organized chronologically.
  - Subject Files, 1967-1977 (Box 495)
  - Subject Files, 1975-1975 (Box 496)
  - Subject Files, 1975-1975 (Box 497)
  - Subject Files, 1975-1975 (Box 498)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 499)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 500)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 501)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 502)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 503)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 504)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 505)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 506)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 507)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1976 (Box 508)
  - Subject Files, 1976-1977 (Box 509)
  - Subject Files, 1977-1977 (Box 510)
  - Subject Files, 1977-1977 (Box 511)
  - Subject Files, 1977-1977 (Box 512)
  - Subject Files, 1977-1977 (Box 513)
  - Subject Files, 1977-1977 (Box 514)
  - Subject Files, 1977-1977 (Box 515)
  - Subject Files, 1977-1978 (Box 516)
  - Ethics Advisory Board and other Subject Files, 1977-1980 (Box 517)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1978 (Box 518)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1978 (Box 519)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1978 (Box 520)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1978 (Box 521)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1978 (Box 522)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1978 (Box 523)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1978 (Box 524)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1978 (Box 525)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1979 (Box 526)
  - Subject Files, 1978-1979 (Box 527)
  - Subject Files, 1979-1979 (Box 528)
  - Subject Files, 1979-1979 (Box 529)
  - Subject Files, 1979-1979 (Box 530)
  - Subject Files, 1979-1980 (Box 531)
  - Subject Files, 1980-1980 (Box 532)
  - Subject Files, 1980-1980 (Box 533)
  - Subject Files, 1980-1980 (Box 534)
  - Subject Files, 1980-1980 (Box 535)
  - Subject Files, 1980-1980 (Box 536)
  - Subject Files, 1980-1980 (Box 537)
  - Subject Files, 1980-1981 (Box 538)
  - Subject Files, 1981-1982 (Box 539)
  - Subject Files, 1979-? (Box 540)
  - Subject Files, 1979-1989 (Box 541)
  - Subject Files, 1979-1989 (Box 819)
  - Subject Files, 1979-1989 (Box 820)
  - Subject Files, 1979-1989 (Box 821)
  - Subject Files, IOM 25th Anniversary, 1990-1997 (Box 542)
  - Background Materials, 1951-1973 (Box 543)
  - Background Materials, 1970-1973 (Box 544)
  - Background Materials, 1973-1979 (Box 545)
  - Background Materials, 1975-1975 (Box 546)
  - Background Materials, 1975-1978 (Box 547)
  - Background Materials, 1976-1976 (Box 548)
  - Background Materials, 1976-1976 (Box 549)
  - Background Materials, 1976-1976 (Box 550)
  - Background Materials, 1976-1976 (Box 551)
  - Background Materials, 1976-1977 (Box 552)
  - Background Materials, 1977-1977 (Box 553)
  - Background Materials, 1977-1977 (Box 554)
  - Background Materials, 1977-1977 (Box 555)
  - Background Materials, 1977-1977 (Box 556)
  - Background Materials, 1977-1977 (Box 557)
  - Background Materials, 1977-1978 (Box 558)
  - Background Materials, 1978-1978 (Box 559)
  - Background Materials, 1978-1978 (Box 560)
  - Background Materials, 1978-1978 (Box 561)
  - Background Materials, 1978-1978 (Box 562)
  - Background Materials, 1978-1978 (Box 563)
  - Background Materials, 1978-1978 (Box 564)
  - Background Materials, 1978-1979 (Box 565)
  - Background Materials, 1979-1979 (Box 566)
  - Background Materials, 1979-1979 (Box 567)
  - Background Materials, 1979-1979 (Box 568)
  - Background Materials, 1979-1980 (Box 569)
  - Background Materials, 1980-1980 (Box 570)
  - Background Materials, 1980-1980 (Box 571)
  - Background Materials, 1980-1980 (Box 572)
  - Background Materials, 1980-1980 (Box 573)
  - Background Materials, 1980-1980 (Box 574)
  - Background Materials, 1973-1980 (Box 822)
  - Background Materials, 1980-2000 (Box 823)
- Series VI: Harvard
  From 1980 to 1983, Hamburg served as director of the university-wide Division of Health Policy Research and Education and John D. MacArthur Professor of Health Policy at Harvard University, Cambridge, MA. The series consists some earlier contacts with Harvard initial correspondence and appointment, miscellaneous policy proposals, co-written with Elena Nightingale, and.applying a cross-disciplinary approach to health policy issues. Also included is Hamburg’s correspondence with MacArthur Foundation relating to his appointment as the John D. MacArthur Professor of Health Policy. The series also contains correspondence, proceedings and handouts from various events in Harvard, in which Hamburg participated, after he left Harvard employment.
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education - initial correspondence and appointment, 1978-1980 (Box 575)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education, 1978-1982 (Box 824)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education, 1980-1981 (Box 576)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education - Health Education Teachers Guides, 1980-1982 (Box 577)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education, 1981- (Box 578)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education, 1981- (Box 579)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education, 1981- (Box 580)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education, 1981-1982 (Box 581)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education, 1981-1982 (Box 582)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education, 1981-1983 (Box 583)
  - Division of Health Policy Research and Education, 1982- (Box 584)
  - Correspondence and events, 1983-1993 (Box 585)
  - Correspondence and events, 1994-1996 (Box 586)
  - Correspondence and events, 1995- (Box 587)
  - Correspondence and events, 1995-1999 (Box 588)
  - Correspondence and events, 1998-2003 (Box 589)
  - MacArthur Foundation - John D. MacArthur Professor of Health Policy appointment, 1980- (Box 590)
  - MacArthur Foundation, 1981- (Box 591)
  - MacArthur Foundation, 1982- (Box 592)
  - Background Materials, 1975-1981 (Box 593)
  - Background Materials, 1979-1982 (Box 594)
  - Background Materials, 1980-2001 (Box 595)
  - Background Materials, 1979-1994 (Box 842)
- Series VII: Board and Advisory Work
  Series consists of meeting minutes, correspondence, reports, memoranda, and printed materials related to the policy decisions of various organizations, where David Hamburg was involved for short-time projects, in advisory capacity or as a trustee. His work for US government and for United Nations agencies is not part of this series; it was processed as separate Series II and Series IX respectively. For more information on Dr. Hamburg’s acitivies related to these institutions, see their correspondence files in Series III.2; for Pocantico Institute of Technology see also the correspondence files for its sponsors, Harvard University John F. Kennedy School of Government and the Rockefeller Foundation. Additional activities related to NIMH are documented in the Stanford series.
  - Subseries VII.1: American Association for the Advancement of Science
    - Meeting minutes, events and correspondence, 1981-2000 (Box 656)
    - Meeting materials, events and correspondence, 1981-2000 (Box 657)
  - Subseries VII.2: American Museum of Natural History
    - Meeting materials, events and correspondence, 1985-1993 (Box 658)
    - Board meetings, media coverage, presidential search, 1993- (Box 659)
    - Board meetings, media coverage, presidential search, 1993- (Box 660)
    - Board meetings, education committee, 1993-1994 (Box 661)
    - Presidential seach, chair search, 1995-1998 (Box 662)
    - Planetarium, Board meeting., 1996-1997 (Box 663)
    - Search committee material and Strategic Planning Committee, 1999-2000 (Box 664)
  - Subseries VII.3: Carter Center
    - Jimmy Carter materials as well as general Carter Ctr., 1988-1996 (Box 665)
    - Jimmy Carter materials as well as general Carter Ctr., 1996-1998 (Box 666)
    - Jimmy Carter materials as well as general Carter Ctr., 1997-1998 (Box 667)
    - Jimmy Carter materials as well as general Carter Ctr., 1998-2000 (Box 668)
    - Jimmy Carter materials as well as general Carter Ctr., 1999-2000 (Box 669)
    - Jimmy Carter materials as well as general Carter Ctr., 2000-2002 (Box 670)
  - Subseries VII.4: The Jacobs Foundation
    - Children & Youth, 1988-1992 (Box 671)
    - Children & Youth, 1992-1994 (Box 672)
    - Children & Youth, 1994-1996 (Box 673)
    - Children & Youth, 1996-1997 (Box 674)
    - Children & Youth, 1997-1998 (Box 675)
  - Subseries VII.5: Mount Sinai Medical Center
    - Board of Trustees meetings, 1980-1993 (Box 676)
    - Board of Trustees meetings, 1994-1996 (Box 677)
    - Board of Trustees meetings, 1994-1997 (Box 678)
    - board of trustees and dean search, 1995-1997 (Box 679)
    - Cardiovascular Advisory Voard; Merger with NYU, 1996-1997 (Box 680)
    - Merger with NYU and Board of Trustees, 1997-1998 (Box 681)
    - Board of Trustees mailings and correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 682)
    - Board of Trustees mailings and correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 683)
    - Board of Trustees mailings and correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 684)
    - Board of Trustees mailings and correspondence, 2000-2000 (Box 685)
    - Board of Trustees mailings and correspondence, 2000-2000 (Box 686)
    - Board of Trustees mailings and correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 687)
  - Subseries VII.6: National Academy of Sciences
    - Correspondence files, 1995-1998 (Box 688)
    - Correspondence files, 1997-1998 (Box 689)
    - Correspondence files, 1998-1999 (Box 690)
    - Correspondence files, 1999-2000 (Box 691)
    - Correspondence files, 1999-2000 (Box 692)
    - Correspondence files, 2000-2001 (Box 693)
    - Correspondence files, 2000-2001 (Box 694)
    - Background materials, 1992-2001 (Box 695)
  - Subseries VII.7: National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)
    - Advisory work and reports, 1974-1986 (Box 696)
  - Subseries VII.8: Pocantico Institute of Science and Technology in International Affairs
    - Correspondence files, 1986-1986 (Box 697)
    - Correspondence files, 1986-1989 (Box 698)
  - Subseries VII.9: The Rockefeller University
    - Correspondence files, 1984-1987 (Box 699)
    - Correspondence files, 1987-1988 (Box 700)
    - Correspondence files, 1988-1990 (Box 701)
    - Correspondence files, 1990-1995 (Box 702)
    - Correspondence files, 1995-1996 (Box 703)
    - Correspondence files, 1997-1998 (Box 704)
    - Correspondence files, 1998-2001 (Box 705)
- Series VIII: Early Career
  Materials dated from 1941-1961 relating to Hamburg's work as a clinical and research psychiatrist at Walter Read Medical Center, Michael Reese Hospital, and NIMH prior to Stanford appointment. Of particular interest is the body of notes, memos, and papers relating to the NIMH research, which sheds light not only on Hamburg's biography but also on the history of medicine, especially psychiatric research practices, in the mid-20th century US. Series includes also background materials on mid-century medical and social science, and notes on patients which will be sealed for 50 years. Series organized into four subseries: General/Chronological, background, NIMH r esearch, and patient files to be sealed; sub-series are organized chronologically, except the backround, which is thematically organized, and follows Hamburg's reference sub categories put in chronological order
  - Clinical & Research Psychiatry Files, 1952-1953 (Box 596)
  - Clinical & Research Psychiatry Files, 1952-1958 (Box 597)
  - Clinical & Research Psychiatry Files, 1953-1962 (Box 598)
  - Clinical & Research Psychiatry Files, 1955-1964 (Box 599)
  - Clinical & Research Psychiatry Files, 1956-1961 (Box 600)
  - Clinical & Research Psychiatry Files, 1958-1962 (Box 601)
  - Clinical & Research Psychiatry Files, 1941-1962 (Box 602)
  - background, 1941-1962 (Box 603)
  - background, 1941-1962 (Box 604)
  - background, 1941-1962 (Box 605)
  - background, 1941-1962 (Box 606)
  - background, 1941-1962 (Box 607)
  - background, 1941-1962 (Box 608)
  - background, 1959-1960 (Box 609)
  - NIMH research, 1960-1962 (Box 610)
  - NIMH research, 1949-1962 (Box 611)
  - Patient Files: Correspondence and Notes, 1957-1966 (Box 612)
    RESTRICTED until 2060
  - Patient Files: Correspondence and Notes, 1948-1960 (Box 613)
  - Patient Files: Therapy Session Notebooks, 1958-1961 (Box 614)
  - Patient Files: Therapy Session Notebooks, 1958 (Box 615)
- Series IX: United Nations